

Kaferholzstrasse 48. Zurich-8057. Switzerland

□ (+41) 762876311 | ■ ankit@ethz.ch | ★ www.ankitjain.ch | ■ 27ankitjain

Summary

A doctoral candidate at ETH Zurich with over 5 years of practical experience in optofluidics and device development. My expertise is in building automated systems with electrical, optical and microfluidic components to carry out research in biology and biochemistry.

Work Experience

ETH Zurich, Institute of Chemical and Bioengineering

Zurich, Switzerland

Jan, 2013 - Aug, 2015

RESEARCH ASSISTANT

Jan, 2018 - PRESENT

- · Successfully integrated optical and electrical components with microfluidic devices
- Automated workflow using LabVIEW, Python and MATLAB
- Prototyped novel microfluidic devices using 3D printing and microfabrication
- Supervised several students on 3D printed droplet-microfluidic devices, phenotyping and cell/gene-recovery from microfluidic droplets
- Successfully collaborated with biochemists, biologists and engineers for directed evolution and cell phenotyping applications

Bangalore, India **Juniper Networks**

HARDWARE ENGINEER • Successfully delivered a high-speed board with a retiming functionality

- Took ownership of high quality hardware from concept to pre-production
- · Designed and verified control path FPGA
- · Designed and tested high speed PCBs
- · Collaborated with PCB layout, Mechanical, Software, Testing and Manufacturing teams

National Instruments Bangalore, India

SUMMER INTERN Jun, 2009 - Jul, 2009

- Worked on a customer-project on real-time signal processing using LabVIEW
- Designed and verified FPGA on National Instrument system

Education

ETH Zurich Zurich, Switzerland

DR. SC. INSTITUTE OF CHEMICAL AND BIOENGINEERING

Jan, 2018 - Present (Tentative Graduation: Feb, 2023)

- Thesis title: «Microfluidic droplet sorting for directed evolution applications»
 - High throughput enzyme-library screening and fluorescence-activated sorting in microfluidic droplets(FADS)
 - Development of generalized assays that obviate the need of surrogate substrates in enzyme evolution in microfluidics
 - Conception and development of novel absorbance-based droplet sorting platform with the highest throughput observed till date

ETH Zurich Zurich, Switzerland

MSC IN MICRO- AND NANOSYSTEMS

Sept, 2015 - Dec, 2017

- Final grade 5.55/6
- Master Thesis title: «On-demand digital barcodes in microfluidic droplets»

IIIT Allahabad

BTECH IN ELECTRONICS AND COMMUNICATION ENGINEERING

Aug, 2009 - Jul, 2013

- Final grade 9.35/10
- Bachelor Thesis title: «Qualification of 48 port 10 GE Interface Test module»

Skills

Microfluidics Droplets, Continuous-flow, Droplet sorting, Quake-Valves, On-chip electrodes, Impedance detection, Flow cytometry, Cell sorting

Optics Fluorescence, Absorption and Photothermal detection, Spectroscopy, Laser-optics

CAD Design (Autocad, Solidworks), Photolithography, Mask Alignment, 3D Printing, PDMS, PMMA, Paper, Surface **Devices**

functionalization

Elec. Systems System architecture, Board design, FPGA development, Microcontrollers, Firmware

Biology Cell culture and preparation, Enzyme kinetics

Programming MATLAB, LabVIEW, Python Languages English, German (B1), Hindi

NOVEMBER 22, 2022 ANKIT JAIN · RÉSUMÉ



Estimating the Three Characteristic Lengths of Plate-like Particles in Suspension

P. BINEL, A. JAIN, A. JAEGGI, D. BIRI, A. K. RAJAGOPALAN, A. J. DEMELLO, M. MAZZOTTI; Small Methods (In press)

Programmable Control of Multiscale Droplets using V-Valves

T. XUE*, A. JAIN* (EQUAL CONTRIBUTION), X. CAO, D. HESS, S. STAVRAKIS, A. J. DEMELLO; Advanced Material Technologies (In press)

Development of a Universal NADH Detection Assay for High Throughput Enzyme Evolution Using Fluorescence Activated Droplet Sorting

G. Kolaitis*, **A. Jain*** (equal contribution), D. Romeis, T. Buryska, M. Steiger, L. Wuerstli, M. Doering, B. Beer, S. Stavrakis, A. J. deMello, V. Sieber; *ChemRxiv*; 10.26434/chemrxiv-2022-jvg5j Target Journal: *ACS Catalysis*

An improved Absorbance Activated Droplet Sorter and its application in the evolution of Aldehyde Dehydrogenase enzyme

A. Jain*, M. Teshika* (equal contribution), T. Buryska, D. Romeis, S. Stavrakis, V. Sieber, A. J. deMello; Manuscript in Preparation; Target Journal: *Small*

Honors & Awards

- ETH Scholarship, 2017
- IIIT-Allahabad Academic Excellence Award (2nd highest GPA), 2010
- President's Scout (by the President of India), 2007

Extracurricular Activity _____

Indian Student Association Zurich President (Vice-President Aug, 2018 - Aug, 2022)

Present Zurich, Switzerland

- Managed core team and oversaw organization of events for students (from 15 to 200 participants)
- Coordinated communication with the students, official student body of ETH (VSETH) and Indian Embassy
- · Designed and maintained the organization website

Art of Living SRI SRI YOGA TEACHER/VOLUNTEER

Present Zurich, Switzerland

- Lead many yoga and meditation sessions in Zurich
- Reached out to public for publicizing workshops

Microfluidics and Microtechnology Summer School Organizer

2018 Zurich, Switzerland

- Scouted speakers for the summer school and coordinated communication with them
- Secured additional sponsorship for the school organization
- Managed daily events during the school

Science Slam Zurich SLAMMER

2019 Zurich, Switzerland

· Participated in numerous Science Slam competitions in venues ranging from Scientific auditoriums to clubs in Zurich

NOVEMBER 22, 2022 ANKIT JAIN · RÉSUMÉ 2

Selected Projects

MICROFLUIDICS

High-throughput screening of enzyme libraries using Fluorescence-activated droplet sorter (FADS)

ETH Zurich, Switzerland

PROF. ANDREW DEMELLO, ETH ZURICH

Jan 2019 – Present

Screening of Haloalkane dehalogenase and alcohol dehydrogenase enzyme libraries for directed evolution experiments in droplet microfluidics using a FADS.

Development of a novel Absorbance-activated droplet sorting (AADS) platform

ETH Zurich, Switzerland

Prof. Andrew deMello, ETH Zurich

Oct 2020 – Present

Developing the fastest AADS platform published to date for directed evolution applications.

Development of a high-throughput cell-deformability-based sorting platform

ETH Zurich, Switzerland

PROF. ANDREW DEMELLO, ETH ZURICH

PROF. ANDREW DEMELLO, ETH ZURICH

Aug 2021 - Present

Mar 2017 - Dec 2017

Electrically actuated cell-sorting platform based on cell-deformability in a non-newtonian viscoelastic fluid.

On-demand digital barcodes in droplets

ETH Zurich, Switzerland

Generation of on-demand monomer droplets, photo-polymerization and subsequent loading into an encapsulating droplet for barcoding applications.

Microfluidic platform for the large-scale screening of C. elegans

ETH Zurich, Switzerland

PROF. ANDREW DEMELLO, ETH ZURICH

Apr, 2016 - Jul, 2016

Developed an image-based automated platform for worm loading, trapping using on-chip pneumatic valves and worm release.

MEMS AND MICROFABRICATION

Fabrication and characterization of MEMS acoustic sensors

ETH Zurich, Switzerland

PROF. CHRISTOFER HIEROLD, ETH ZURICH

Feb, 2016 - Aug, 2016

Aided in the development of coupled mass-based MEMS acoustic sensors. The tasks included design of test structures, etching (RIE) of devices, imaging using SEM, and characterization via Laser Doppler Vibrometer.

Fabrication and characterization of a MEMS accelerometer

ETH Zurich, Switzerland

EMBEDDED MEMS LAB PRACTICAL COURSE, ETH ZURICH

Oct, 2015 - Nov, 2015

BOARD AND FPGA DESIGN

Design of 4X100GE CXP optics based physical interface card

Bangalore, India

JUNIPER NETWORKS, BANGALORE

Sep, 2013 – Jul, 2015

Designed and tested a high-speed PCB that housed four 100GE CXP optical interfaces, Regenerative repeaters (retimers), a control path FPGA, and associated clocking, power and miscellaneous control devices.

Qualification of 48 port 10 GE interface test module

Bangalore, India

JUNIPER NETWORKS, BANGALORE

Apr, 2013 – Jun, 2013

Tested PCB which was used for validating various types of interfaces such as 10GE, I2C, SGMII, PCIe and MDIO. The board housed regenerative repeaters for looping back 10GE traffic, control path CPLD, and various power loads.

Implementation of a JPEG encoder on FPGA

Prayagraj, India

Prof. Dr. Neteesh Purohit, IIITA

Jan, 2012 – May, 2012

Developed and implemented an efficient architecture for JPEG image compression encoder with a 2-stage pipeline without using any hardware multipliers (just for fun).

November 22, 2022 Ankit Jain · Résumé 3